Maxim Kropotov

maxim.kropotov@gmail.com | github.com/undeadcat

Software developer who's passionate about building a product for real users. Don't believe in something being 'done' or 'not my job' until the users are happy.

Technical interests: highly available distributed systems, developer tooling, source code analysis & compilers.

Languages: Shipped production code in C#, Java, Kotlin, TypeScript, JavaScript. Minor experience with F#, Python (Jupyter notebooks, ad-hoc data analysis), Ruby, Golang, C++, Scala.

Databases / Data Stores: MySQL, Kafka, Elasticsearch, Redis, MongoDB, Cassandra, PostgreSQL, MS SQL.

Work Experience

oct. 2019 - present

Bolt, Tallinn (Estonia)

Staff Software Engineer, Rides Marketplace Group

- Led project to split order system monolith into smaller services to allow teams to develop product features independently.
- Implemented archiving of pricing data, taking an existing solution and updating it to be reusable for other services.
- Led team's effort to prepare systems for uneventful New Year's Eve last two years (10x+ regular peak load).

Senior Software Engineer, Rides / Order Team

Part of team responsible for 80+ critical microservices: ridehailing search, dispatching and order storage.

- Led cross-functional projects to deliver features: writing tech specs, ensuring clear communication, leading development, managing feature rollout.
- Migrated critical parts of order system to Redis Cluster.
- Free-time project: contributed to Bolt IntelliJ IDE plugin to simplify working with Bolt backend code.

Software Engineer, Campaigns Team

• Started a project to convert a business-critical process from a batch job to event processing. Increased throughput by ~4x.

nov. 2016 - oct. 2019

Software Engineer: JetBrains, St.Petersburg (Russia)

Worked on Javascript and TypeScript support in Webstorm and IntelliJ IDEAbased IDEs: support for refactoring code in the IDE, new language features, type resolution, etc.

- · Worked directly with end-user requests every day.
- Implemented refactorings for React components.
- Contributed to a 3rd-party plugin to support styled-components framework in IntelliJ IDEs.

Software Engineer: Kontur, Ekaterinburg (Russia)

Kontur.Elba — Part of small cross-functional team building friendly online accounting service for small businesses in Russia.

Building product features, managing releases, solving user issues with the tech support team, maintaining production and staging environments.

- Implemented several features relating to health monitoring: storing logs in Elasticsearch, integrating JavaScript error reporting.
- Used emitting MSIL code to optimize a service.

Internships:

- **Kontur.Diadoc**: Optimized a service writing Event Sourcing events to Apache Cassandra by ~4x.
- **Kontur.Extern**: Implemented a web app for monitoring servers of Kanso distributed file system (in-house Google File System clone, hundreds of terabytes scale).

Education

2008 – 2013 BS, Mathematics and Computer Science, Ural Federal University, Ekaterinburg